Inventory of the Roland Tasho photographs
Hoover Institution Archives
Roland Tasho photographs
1968-2000
1990-1999
2000C52
Hoover Institution Archives
4 cardfile boxes, 6 manuscript boxes (2.3 linear feet)
Photographs depicting the social and political conditions in Albania from the Communist era to 2000 and the Kosovo refugee crisis in 1999.
Tasho, Roland.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Albanian photographer.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of photographs that detail the socio-political climate of Albania from the 1960s to 2000. Photographs include themes of education, agriculture, industry, religion, and politics. The collection mainly focuses on the political turmoil of the 1990s from the fall of Communism, the 1996 disputed elections, the Albanian Unrest of 1997 ( Rebelimi i vitit 1997), demonstrations after the assassination of Albanian member of parliament Azem Hajdari, and the Kosovo refugee crisis in 1999.
The collection maintains the original titles given by the creator. The photographs are organized chronologically and related subjects are grouped together.
Albania--Pictorial works.; Albania--Politics and government.; Kosovo (Serbia) History--Pictorial works.; Kosovo (Serbia)--History--Civil War, 1998-1999.; Refugees--Pictorial works.; Yugoslavia--Pictorial works.
- Life Under Communism, 1968-1990
  - 1960s
    - New passenger train, 1968 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, 1960s-1990 (Box-folder 1:2-11)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes images of everyday life in Albania including people, towns, seasons, work, technology, industry, and leisure activities.
  - 1970s
    - "Various themes of Albania under communism,", 1970-1990 (Box-folder 1:12-20)
      Includes images of people and village life.
    - "Life in Albania under communism,", 1970-1982 (Box-folder 1:21-27)
      Includes black and white images of family life, education, agriculture, factory work, military, and entertainment.
    - Journalists of Ylli monthly magazine, 1970 (Box-folder 1:28)
    - "Youth Amateurs Concert" in Korça, 1970 (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Military, 1970s-1990s
      - Military, 1970s-1990s (Box-folder 1:30-31)
      - Political/military celebrations and monuments, circa 1970 (Box-folder 1:32)
      - "All the people are soldiers,", 1970-1980s (Box-folder 1:33)
    - Politics and government, 1970s
      - Voting in Tirana, 1970 (Box-folder 1:34)
      - May 1st celebrations in Tirana, 1971 (Box-folder 1:35-36)
      - Albanian dictator Enver Hoxha, 1970s (Box-folder 1:37)
        Includes reprints of photographs of Enver Hoxha as a partisan leader in the 1940s (not taken by the creator).
      - Enver Hoxha meets with artists, 1975 (Box-folder 1:38)
    - "Mjeksi vitet," healthcare, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 1:39)
    - Sports, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 1:40-41)
    - Education, 1970-1981 (Box-folder 1:42-47)
      Includes images of classroom activities, a field trip to the Lenin-Stalin Museum, and student volunteer work building apartments and the Progozina-Fier railway.
    - Industry, 1970s (Box-folder 2:1-6)
      Includes images of mining and factory work.
    - Agriculture, 1970-1984 (Box-folder 2:7-10)
    - Cultural activities, 1975-1987 (Box-folder 2:11-14)
      Includes images of a ballet, music recitals, and plays.
    - Towns, 1970s
      - Korça, Durrës, Fier, Tirana, Librazhd, Elbasan, Shkodra, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 2:15-16)
      - Views of Saranda and Korça, circa 1970 (Box-folder 2:17)
      - District of Kukës, 1970 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - 1980s
    - Education, 1980-1989
      - Students, circa 1980s (Box-folder 2:19)
      - Military school, Tirana, 1983 (Box-folder 2:20)
      - State University of Tirana “Enver Hoxha,”, 1985 (Box-folder 2:21)
      - Students at Agricultural University, 1987 (Box-folder 2:22)
      - Teaching traffic rules to kids, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:23)
      - National Library at the University of Tirana, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:24)
      - Children’s program at Albanian State TV, 1989 (Box-folder 2:25)
      - Youth Voluntary work, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2:26)
    - Monuments and Arts, circa 1980
      - The National Folk Festival, Gjirokaster, 1988 (Box-folder 2:27)
      - Monuments of Socialist Realism, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:28)
      - Drawing of Heroes of Socialist Realism, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:29)
      - Monument of National Hero Scanderbeg, includes views of Tirana, Apollonia (Fier), and Butrint (Saranda), circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:30)
      - Visits to Enver Hoxha's house in Gjirdkastra, 1980 (Box-folder 2:31-32)
      - Museum House, circa 1980 (Box-folder 2:33)
      - President Ramiz Alia and Prime Minister Adil Garçani, 1986 (Box-folder 2:34)
    - Industry, circa 1980
      - Artisan enterprise, 1987 (Box-folder 2:35)
      - Miners of Vallas mine, 1985 (Box-folder 2:36)
      - Ferro-Chrome Mill in Elbasan, 1985 (Box-folder 2:37)
      - Glass mill and carpet factory, Kavaja, 1984 (Box-folder 2:38)
      - Durrës Port and Railway Station, 1980s (Box-folder 2:39)
      - Clothes factory in Korça and Shkodra, 1985 (Box-folder 2:40-41)
      - "Dinamo” Mill in Tirana, 1984 (Box-folder 2:42)
      - “Banja” Hydro Power station, 1980s (Box-folder 2:43)
      - Construction work in Kukës, 1985 (Box-folder 2:44)
      - Agriculture work, Fier, 1982 (Box-folder 2:45)
- Post-Communist Albania, 1989-1999
  - Politicians, 1980s-1990s (Box-folder 3:1-5)
  - "Social Themes,", 1990s (Box-folder 3:6-7)
    Includes images of people, industry, body-building, and buildings.
  - Military, 1990s (Box-folder 3:8-11)
  - Religion, 1990-1999
    - Reopening of the First Church, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 3:12)
      Includes images of Mother Teresa's visit in 1991 and the Pope John Paul II visit in 1992.
    - Churches and mosques, 1998 (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Tombs of Mother Teresa's mother and sister, undated (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Islam in Tirana, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Holy Site of “Shna Ndov” (Saint Andrew), Laç, Albania, undated (Box-folder 3:16)
  - The Foundation of the First Opposition Party, 1990 December 12 (Box-folder 3:17)
    Includes Partia Demokratike e Shqipërisë leaders: Neritan Ceka, Sali Berisha, Arben Imami, Gramoz Pashko, Eduard Selami, and Aleksandër Meksi.
  - Student hunger strikes, 1991 February 17-20 (Box-folder 3:18-20)
  - Hunger strike of miners, Valis, Tirana, 1991 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Sale of first opposition newspaper Rilindja Demokratike, 1991 January (Box-folder 3:22-23)
  - 10th Congress of the party of Labor, 1991 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Last Communist dictator Ramiz Alia on election day, 1991 March 31 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Demonstrations to overthrow the Socialist government, 1991 May 21 (Box-folder 3:26-28)
  - Students celebrate by burning the posters of Enver Hoxha and Ramiz Tafë Alia, 1991 October 16 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Student demonstrations, 1992 January-February (Box-folder 3:30)
  - 1992 elections
    - Sali Berisha, election victory, 1992 March (Box-folder 3:31)
    - Democratic Party victory, 1992 March 22 (Box-folder 3:32)
    - Celebrating the Democratic party victory, “combine”district, Tirana, 1999 March (Box-folder 3:33)
    - “The Victory of the Democratic Party,", 1992 (Box-folder 3:34-37)
  - US Secretary of State James Baker's visit to Tirana, 1992 (Box-folder 3:38)
  - Free passing at the border with Greece, Kakavijë, Albania, 1992 (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Anti-Communist demonstrations, Shkodra, Albania, 1992 (Box-folder 3:40)
  - Burning a statue of dictator Enver Hoxha, Tirana Main Square, 1992 October 16 (Box-folder 3:41)
  - Bread sale, 1992 (Box-folder 3:42)
  - Trials, 1992-1993
    - Trial of Politburo members, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3:43)
    - Trial against Greek minority activist, 1993 (Box-folder 3:44)
    - Only public execution, Fier, Albania, 1993 (Box-folder 3:45)
  - The opening of the Coca Cola factory, 1994 (Box-folder 3:46)
  - Italian Aid and the “Pelican” operation, 1994 (Box-folder 3:47)
  - Hunger strike, 1994 (Box-folder 3:48-49)
  - First Albanian modern highway, 1996 (Box-folder 3:50)
  - Bomb explosion in front of pyramid [scheme] company VEFA supermarket, 1996 February (Box-folder 3:51)
  - 1996 elections
    - The manipulated elections, 1996 May 26 (Box-folder 3:52-53)
    - Opposition protests after the manipulated elections, 1996 May 26-28 (Box-folder 3:54-58, Box-folder 4:1-5)
    - Democratic Party campaign rallies and celebrations, 1999 May-June (Box-folder 4:6-9)
    - Hunger strike of the Democratic Alliance Party and the Social-Democratic Party after elections, 1996 (Box-folder 4:10-11)
    - State violence against Opposition leaders, Tirana Main Square, 1996 May 28 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Miss Europe Contest, 1996 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Beating of a journalist and burning of the offices of the Koha Jone newspaper, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Albanian Rebellion of 1997
    - Funeral of a murdered Democratic Party member, 1997 January (Box-folder 4:15)
    - Fair with pyramid scheme companies, 1996 (Box-folder 4:16)
    - Destruction in Gjirokaster, 1997 (Box-folder 4:17)
    - Road blocks, 1997 (Box-folder 4:18)
    - Student solidarity, 1997 (Box-folder 4:19)
    - Protests against the pyramid schemes, 1997 January-February (Box-folder 4:20)
    - Ammunition seized after rebellion, 1998 (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Destruction of Orthodox icons, Voskopoja, 1997 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Older communists celebrating Enver Hoxha's birthday, 1997 October 16 (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Bunker, Durrës, 1998 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Police controls, 1998 (Box-folder 4:25)
  - Roma, Gjirokastre, 1998 (Box-folder 4:26)
  - "Throne-Pretender" Leka Zogu, campaign to restore monarchy rule in Albania, 1998 (Box-folder 4:27)
  - Prisons, 1998 (Box-folder 4:28-30)
  - Village life in Tirana, Lezhë, and Durrës, 1998 (Box-folder 4:31)
  - Komuniste, the Albanian Communist Party reborn, Tirana, 1998 (Box-folder 4:32)
  - Assassination of MP Azem Hajdari, 1997-1998
    - Demonstrations and destruction after the murder of opposition MP Azem Hajdari, 1998 September 14 (Box-folder 4:33-35)
    - Location of MP Azem Hajdari's murder, 1998 September 12 (Box-folder 4:36)
    - Protesters steal tanks in protest, 1998 September (Box-folder 4:37)
    - Funeral, 1998 September 15 (Box-folder 4:38)
    - Birth of the son of MP Azem Hajdari, visits by S. Berisha and Pjeter Arbnori, circa 1998 (Box-folder 4:39)
  - Dormitory strikes, 1998 December (Box-folder 4:40)
  - Destruction of Enver Hoxha monument, circa 1998 (Box-folder 4:41)
  - Removal of Yugoslav flag from the Yugoslav Embassy, 1999 January (Box-folder 4:42)
  - Tobacco factory “Veve," Librazhd, Albania, 1999 (Box-folder 4:43)
  - Daily life in Tirana, 1999 (Box-folder 4:44)
  - Opposition rally following the election of Fatos Nano, 1999 October (Box-folder 4:45)
  - Resignation of Prime Minister Pandeli Majko and appointment of Prime Minister Ilir Meta, 1999 October 26-28 (Box-folder 4:46)
  - Textile and thermocentral buildings, 1999 October (Box-folder 4:47)
  - “Fishers Bridge,” Tirana, 1999 November (Box-folder 4:48)
  - Winter without electricity, 1999 (Box-folder 4:49)
  - Voluntary blood donation, Tirana, 1999 November (Box-folder 4:50)
  - Tirana’s Main Maternity Hospital, 1999 November (Box-folder 4:51)
  - Construction and new restaurants in Durrës and Tirana, 1999 November (Box-folder 4:52)
  - Independence and liberation days, 1999 November 28-29 (Box-folder 4:53)
  - Politicans, 1990s (Box-folder 4:54-55)
    Includes Albanian and US politicians.
  - Konferenca Gjyqësore Kombëtare, 1999 December (Box-folder 4:56)
  - Harry T. Fultz Technical School, 1999 (Box-folder 4:57)
  - Velija, Vebi, undated (Box-folder 4:58)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1990 (Box-folder 4:59, Box-folder 5:13-17)
- Kosovo Refugee Crisis, 1999-2000
  - Refugee camps, 1999
    - Kosovar refugee artists, "Dinamo" factory, 1999 February-May (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Rrashbull, Durrës, 1999 February- May (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Manzë-Durrës refugee camp, 1999 March-April (Box-folder 5:3-5)
      Includes images of camp life, food distribution, and official delegation visits.
    - Kukës refugee camp, 1999 April (Box-folder 5:6-13, Box-folder 6:1-6)
    - Swimming Pool refugee camp, Tirana, 1999 April- May (Box-folder 6:7-9, Box-folder 7:1-9)
      Includes images of the Albanian civil defence authorities and the Greek government, who set up the camp.
    - Sports Palace camp, Tirana, 1999 (Box-folder 7:10-11, Box-folder 8:1-5)
      Includes images of "SOS Kosova" TV program, camp life, and refugee transfers and departures back to Kosovo.
    - Pogradec refugee camp, 1999 May (Box-folder 8:6-9)
      Includes images of camp life, Greek military food distribution, and local politician's visit.
    - Workers resort palace, Korca, 1999 April-May (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Demonstrations at the Yugoslav Embassy, Tirana, 1999 March (Box-folder 9:1-2)
  - Miscellaneous refugee and aid, 1999 April-September (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Demonstration for Kosovo, Tirana Square, 1999 April (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Politicians, 1999 April-October (Box-folder 9:5)
    Includes images of Paskal Milo, Adem Demaçi, Ibrahim Rugova, Rexhep Qosja, and investment banker George Soros.
  - Kosovar refugees in a nursing home for the old, Tirana, 1999 May (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Tony Blair's visit to Tirana, Albania, 1999 May 18 (Box-folder 9:7)
  - United States Delegation in Albania, 1999 June 22 (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Exhibition of paintings by Kosovar children, Tirana, 1999 June (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Pristina, Kosovo, 1999 September-October (Box-folder 9:10-11)
  - Kosovars in Albanian home, 1999 May (Box-folder 9:12)
  - Homeless Kosovar refugees who remained in Durrës, 1999 December (Box-folder 4:60)
  - Volunteers at Albanian Center for Human Rights offering services and recreation activities to Kosovar children, 1999 (Box-folder 4:61)
  - Kosovo, 2000 April-May (Box-folder 4:61-67, Box 10)
    Over 180 photographs that focus on post-Kosovo war daily life. Includes images of people, buildings, the National Library, graveyards, politicians, and the remaining destruction from the 1999 crisis.